Thanks Pat, thanks to the Royal Institution for having me back, this is one of my favorite places to come visit
and I thought that I would in the tradition of Michael Faraday and Humphrey Davy,
and all the greats who've stood more or less in this place
Begin the lecture by doing an experiment.
Now I'm a theoretical physicist. I'm not an experimenter, so don't get your hopes up too high
But I would like to do an experiment that illuminates the fundamental nature of motion.
Ok so you see here. We have an object. It's a book you can buy it at the finest book stores everywhere
and we're going to observe what happens to the object.
Nothing much happens to the object is the short answer to it
it just sits there, but I can if I push on the object get it moving and
then if I stop pushing, it stops moving -- the nature of motion there being demonstrated to you right there.
So if you were the kind of systematic thinker that let's say Aristotle was,
you would go from a demonstration like that to a very deep picture of how the world works at a fundamental level.
You would say that there is something called the natural state for the book to be in,
which is just sitting there motionless.
You would say that if you don't do anything an object stays in its natural state.
But if you apply a force to it -- an impetus -- you can change its natural state.
You can cause it to start moving and you notice when I then stopped pushing
it stopped. It returns to its natural state.
So you invent what philosophers would call an ontology or a metaphysics or a fundamental view
of what the world is made of. It's made of things that have natural states.
And if they're not staying stationary and unchanging in their natural states,
it is because something is changing them. When there is motion there is a Mover.
And you can go from this simple idea to a theory of physics as Aristotle did
and you can in fact go beyond that to a theory of metaphysics that explains not just the motion of things
but more or less how everything changes and transforms at all.
You can even go all the way back -- you can say well, okay
this thing is moving because this other thing is pushing it. But what causes that other thing to be moving?
If you trace the chain of motion and movers backward you eventually
would need to reach an Unmoved Mover and thereby prove the existence of God
without ever leaving the lecture hall right here.
This way of thinking is not only a systematization of some very simple physics experiments you can do,
it also sort of accords well with our everyday experience.
When you see something moving or not moving, it's because something is moving it or not moving it.
So there became a philosophical tradition, which tried to go from the physics of it to a deeper understanding
claiming that everything that Happens -- whether it's motion or otherwise -- Happens for a Reason.
This is not just a bumper sticker you can buy,
this is a very venerable philosophical maxim known as the Principle of Sufficient Reason.
So here you have Aristotle, Spinoza followed up with his version of the Principle of Sufficient Reason
and then Leibniz on the right German philosopher who also invented Calculus
They all put forward this idea that we can understand how the world works at a deep level by providing
explanations for everything we see in it. Nothing happens randomly,
nothing "just happens" -- there's always a Purpose, a Cause, a Reason Why Things Happen.
You might be forgiven for thinking that the ultimate purpose was ever more grandiose hairstyles for professional philosophers
Even if Leibniz sort of had some artificial help there in in in his coiffeur
The problem is that this is not right.
The problem is that the world does not work this way at a fundamental level.
There's two problems -- one is it's not right; the other is despite the fact that it's not right, we haven't abandoned it yet.
So we have learned a lot about how the world works because of the progress of science and philosophy
but we still talk a language that is handed down to us by Aristotle, Spinoza, and Leibniz.
Now people have tried to fix the language -- here is Bertrand Russell, a more modern philosopher
trying to point out that the very idea of Cause and Effect
is no longer fundamental in our understanding of the world.
He says, "The Law of Causality, I believe, Like much that passes muster among philosophers, is a relic of a bygone age. Surviving, like the monarchy..."
He couldn't resist, right? Like, I'm just the messenger here. This is not -- I'm not saying this --
"Surviving, like the monarchy, only because it is erroneously supposed to do no harm."
Now many people would be surprised to hear the news that science has done away with the Principle of Cause and Effect.
But I'm not gonna undo that -- it's actually true! It's not that there is no such thing as cause and effect.
It's that it is not a fundamental principle of how reality works.
It is a very useful helpful way of thinking it about things at a macroscopic --
what we will call an emergent -- level of reality.
But it is nowhere to be found in the most fundamental laws of physics.
And that difference puts us in the position of Wile E Coyote, a famous American cartoon character.
I don't know how popular the Roadrunner is in uh in the UK? Good.
So Wile E Coyote you will remember if you're of the right age
had this thing that he did every single episode where he would run off a cliff.
And because it's cartoon physics -- not either Aristotelian or Newtonian physics -- he would not fall down
until he noticed that he was not standing on anything.
He would look around, and then oh! and then he would fall down, okay
We are all Wile E Coyote in some sense and in the following sense --
This cliff, this solid surface that we used to be walking on, is our old fashioned,
Aristotelian et al., notion of Causes and Effects and Purposes and Meanings in the world.
We have left that behind. The fundamental rules of nature, according to our best scientific understanding, don't work that way
but we haven't adapted. We still speak a language as if Cause and Effect, Purpose and Goals,
and Reasons Why are the fundamental way the world works.
So one of our challenges should be to reconcile the
deep down vocabulary of the world given to us by physics and modern science
with what philosophers call the Manifest Image -- the immediately accessible view of the world we have.
After all, physicists love to make fun of Aristotle and say how wrong he was, but look --
the book does stop moving, right?  That's not a mistake!
That is an accurate way of talking about the world.
Cause and Effect are accurate useful ways of talking about the world. You can be accurate without being fundamental.
Our goal is to show how at different levels of analysis -- different levels of squinting at the world --
reveal different rules, regularities, and even vocabularies for speaking.
So I like to trace the origin of this shift from Aristotle to Bertrand Russell for example
It's actually a long series of very very interesting thoughts and experiments over hundreds of years
between Aristotle and let's say Isaac Newton.  I like to give some credit to this guy Ibn Sina who sometimes
Romanized or Latinized as "Avicenna". He was a Persian polymath in the Islamic Golden Age in around the Year 1000
and as a modern day theoretical physicist I find Ibn Sina extremely annoying.
because his day job was he was a doctor
he was his interests were in health and human anatomy and he wrote many books about the human body
and on weekends he invented new fundamental laws of physics.
We can't do that anymore, it's more work now. The low-hanging fruit has been picked.
So Ibn Sina was thinking about Aristotelian notions of motion and so forth
and what he pointed out for the very first time was that this idea that the book stops moving
shouldn't be thought of as the book returning to its natural state of motion
because if the book was not on the table here in a room,
but rather out in space -- like the spacecraft -- if it were in the vacuum
the book would just keep moving at a constant velocity. What we now call Conservation of Momentum or Conservation of Inertia.
Now Ibn Sina didn't like this idea. He didn't even like the idea of a vacuum.
In the year 1000 we weren't sure whether there were any vacua ("vacuums")
so he put forward this idea, but it was seized upon by later thinkers.
There's no such thing as natural motion versus being pushed -- the natural motion of things is just to keep moving
you don't need to keep things pushed.
And of course Galileo helped develop this idea. He pointed out that if you think of the
fundamental starting point of motion as constant motion with the uniform velocity,
and then put in things like friction and dissipation and air resistance afterward,
you get a much more accurate, precise, quantitative feeling for what happens in the world.
So the secret thing that sneaks in is not just a new way to torture first-year physics
students with inclined planes and pulleys and so forth.
There's a fundamentally new way of looking at the world.
The world is not made of Motions that have a Mover, Effects that have Causes
There are things that are doing their thing according to some rigorous
mathematical laws of physics, some conservation laws very often, such as conservation of momentum.
And of course once Isaac Newton came along and put together his theory
of physics and motion and mechanics we had a much deeper version of Conservation
what you could call Conservation of Information. And even though it's sort of in some implicit
sense due to Isaac Newton, it was really Pierre Simone Laplace who stuck his neck out and really
understood the implications of Newtonian mechanics. Laplace points out the following thing.
Let's imagine that we believed Newton's laws of motion -- which they did at the time --
and in fact I'll point out we updated them since then but it's not a fundamentally -- not in a way that really changes this particular analysis.
Laplace says look, think of two billiard balls bouncing into each other and scattering off.
Now he takes these in the tradition of Ibn Sina and Galileo and so forth to be physicist billiard balls
They make no noise, they have no air resistance, are on a frictionless surface.
So they scatter off and they go their own way. The traditional question we would ask of our students is, if you
gave me the information at the start of the experiment -- so where the balls were, and how they were moving --
I could tell you -- I could solve the equations and tell you how they would evolve thereafter.
But what Laplace points out is that in fact you could give me the
information about what the billiard balls are doing at any moment in time.
You could not only tell what's going to happen next, according to Newton's laws, you could say what did happen before that.
The information necessary to tell you what's happening in those billiard balls is contained equally well in every moment of their existence.
So he says imagine a vast intellect. Later commentators thought that "vast intellect" was insufficiently sexy,
so they said imagine a Demon -- which we now call Laplace's Demon --
and of course if we had been at 20th or a 21st century commentator would have been imagine a really big computer.
That knew the position and the velocity of everything in the universe and all the laws of physics
and had apparently infinite calculational abilities -- computational capacity.
To this vast intellect, Laplace says, there is no difference between the present the past and the future.
The future and the past are equally transparent and known as the present is, because they are determined by the Laws of Nature.
So this sets up a whole long, centuries-long debate about Determinism and Freewill and etc
But there's something deeper that gets glossed over sometimes and it is worth bringing out
It's not that anything goes, but the vocabulary has changed.
Aristotle would have said if things are moving, there's something moving them. There's a Cause or a Reason Why they are moving.
Laplace says they just obey equations. What that means is that rather than a cause-and-effect relationship,
we have patterns in the universe. Think about the integers, right?
The number zero, one, two, three, and also negative minus one, minus two, minus three...
There's a pattern there. If you tell me any one number, if you say "three", I know what the number before that was.
It was two. I know what the number after that's gonna be, it's gonna be four.
But I don't think that three is the cause of four or vice-versa. There's just a pattern that relates all those numbers to each other.
Laplace is saying the laws of physics are like that.
It's not that there is an impulse, an enchantment, a Guiding Force
it's just there's a pattern that says if-this-then-that-and-vice-versa
and this way of thinking about how the world works at a deep level is something we have yet to truly absorb.
Of course Laplace was not right. He didn't know about the true laws of physics,
he thought that Newton's laws were more or less correct he had every reason to believe that was true
but since then we have Relativity and Quantum Mechanics and so forth, so we have a better idea now of what the laws fundamentally are.
In fact, one of the bold claims I want to make
-- and you're willing to disbelieve me if you want, but you would be incorrect --
is that the Laws of Physics underlying everyday life are today completely known.
Here, I put on a slide just in case. This sounds very much like one of those incredibly
dopey pretentious statements that scientists have made for hundreds of years right? Scientists, especially
physicists -- my tribe -- are very very famous for saying, "You know any day now, we'll have it all figured out,
we'll have the Theory of Everything." This was especially common in the late 19th Century.
People were saying, "Yes, we have you know Mechanics and Thermodynamics and Electromagnetism,
any day now we'll have all the physics figured out."
And then of course it all went to Hell because they invented Relativity and Quantum Mechanics and so forth.
I'm not saying that. I'm not making any statement whatsoever about how close we are to
understanding all of the laws of physics or everything we are made of.
What I'm saying is we know some of the laws of physics some of the things that we are made of,
and more importantly the regime that we do understand -- the domain of validity of our current knowledge --
includes everything in this room.  Includes everything that you experience in the everyday regime of your life,
as long as your everyday regime is not that of an experimental particle physicist.
You are made of atoms. You are made of particles: electrons, protons, neutrons.
Those protons and neutrons are made of quarks: 'up' and 'down' quarks
And these particles feel forces and there's basically four forces that are relevant here: gravity pulling everything together,
electromagnetism pulling together unlike charges and pushing away like charges.
There's a strong nuclear force that binds those quarks together to make the proton and the neutron.
And there's a weak nuclear force which is almost irrelevant except it helps the Sun shine so that's kind of important.
The weak nuclear force converts protons to neutrons and vice versa by spitting out a particle called a neutrino.
Okay, so four particles: electron, up quark, down quark, neutrino. Four forces: gravity, electromagnetism, strong, and weak.
... and that's it. We know there are other particles. There are muons. There are top quarks etc
You can argue over the exact cutoff for everyday life, okay?
But you're made of these particles and everything you see with your eyes, touch with your fingers, taste with your tongue
made of these particles. And the statement I want to make is that understanding of what you're made of -- the particles and the forces, the laws that they obey --
is true. It's not gonna go away. It's not like Epicycles or
Phlogiston or Caloric, these ideas that we had in the past that we showed later were completely wrong
It's an idea that a thousand years from now or a million years from now we're still going to believe that these particles exist, that the rules that we now know are
accurate ways of talking about how they behave inside you. We might get a deeper understanding
you might realize that Space and Time themselves aren't fundamental.
We certainly don't know how to take these laws and build them up to make Biology and Chemistry and Economics or anything like that.
But at this particular level -- What are the particles and forces that you and I are made out of, what are the equations that tell us how they behave?
We know that. And I know that you don't believe me because I'm just showing you a cartoon. You're thinking to yourself
I'm not gonna believe this until I see the equation. So here you go
This is the equation. I'm very grateful to the Royal Institution for giving me these six hours, so I can explain
all of the terms in this equation in great detail. But that's okay, you don't need to know all the details.
As you see from the labels on the equation this is a single equation that more or less is the information
that the modern-day version of Laplace's Demon would need to tell you what happens in the world.
This is the answer to the question, you tell me what the configuration of stuff in the world is right now
this equation tells you what it will be a little bit in the future, what it was a little bit in the past.
It's a quantum mechanical equation, so if you observe the system,
one of the things about quantum mechanics is you can only predict probabilities not certainties.
But this is the equation that tells you what those probabilities are. It includes Quantum Mechanics, Spacetime,
all the matter particles that we're made of as well as all the forces that we know about and of course the Higgs field
Lurking in the background that we finally had evidence for back in 2012.
What you don't see in this picture is anything that Aristotle would recognize as a Final Cause
or anything that Leibniz would recognize as the Reason Why a certain event is happening.
The language being spoken here is that of patterns and differential equations,
not of causes, purposes, meanings, and there's no values here. There's no judgments.
This equation -- what we call the Core Theory of Physics --
which has all the particle physics and also all the gravity that we know about.
The Core Theory doesn't pass judgment on you or me.  It doesn't tell us what is right from wrong.
It just tells you what is going to happen. Now even though I showed you the equation, you might still not be happy because you say,
"Well I only trust equations that can fit on a T-shirt." So I have the experimental evidence that
the Core Theory can fit on a T-shirt. We're in good shape now. I know what you're thinking. I've given this talk before, different forms.
You're thinking, "Fine, you guys, you physicists, you have your particles and your forces.
But it's just the same kind of hubris to say that we're not going to discover new
particles and forces that you don't know about yet. How do you know that there's not new particles, Mr. Smartypants Physicist?"
And of course, there's two answers for that. One is it's almost certainly true that there are
new particles and forces that we've not yet discovered.
Remember, all I'm claiming is that we've discovered the particles and forces relevant to our everyday lives.
As a working theoretical physicist, I certainly hope there are new particles and forces in understanding,
I'm just saying that whatever we discover along those lines is not going to affect your Biology.
It's not gonna affect your Psychology.
It's not gonna affect the motion of the particles that do make up you that we know about right now.
So how do we know that? That's a very grandiose claim.
It's one that we really could not have made in years past. It turns out to be a very specific feature of the way
that this equation works. It is based on the principles of what we call Quantum Field Theory.
Field Theory is the idea that what you think is a particle like an electron or a photon is really a
vibration in a field filling all of space. Why does it look like a particle instead of looking like a field?
That's where the Quantum comes in. Quantum says that when you look at these things that make up the world
they come to you in discrete packets of stuff. We call those packets of stuff "particles."
So Quantum Field Theory says the world is made of fields, but Quantum Mechanics
gives us the rules for observing them so we can talk about them in terms of particles.
And then it goes on to draw implications from that idea.
So here's one simple implication of Quantum Field Theory called Crossing Symmetry
that's usually taught as a little technical tool in Quantum Field Theory, but it actually has extremely profound implications.
So let's say we imagine that there is a particle or a force or a field that we haven't yet found
in our experiments that might in fact play an important role in human biology or neuroscience.
How would that work?
Well the first thing that a physicist would do given the proposition that there's a new particle is start drawing these pictures
what are called Feynman Diagrams. Named after Richard Feynman, my predecessor at Caltech.
My most famous accomplishment as a physicist is I sit at the desk that Richard Feynman used to sit at.
It is the desk given to the most senior theoretical physicist at Caltech
who is not senior enough to get a brand new desk when they get there. So I got that one.
These Feynman diagrams do two things: they number one show us what can happen. They are pictures of actual processes.
So the diagram on the left, you have an ordinary particle at the bottom. Let's say a proton.
At the top, the red line is some new particle, some particle that we've hypothesized
and we're imagining there's some new interaction or some old interaction
maybe electromagnetism or the weak nuclear force
via which this new particle can interact with the particle that we know about -- the proton --
so you read the diagram from left to right it says that the new particle comes in,
a proton comes in, and they scatter off of each other by exchanging some Boson --
some photon or some new Boson that we haven't heard about okay
Number one, the diagram tells you that can happen,
but number two, there are rules for attaching numbers to these diagrams.
So if you're a graduate student in physics this diagram will strike fear into your heart, because you go, "oh no
I have to calculate a scattering amplitude." And the diagram lets you do that. It tells you the probability
the two particles will come in and scatter off.
Now Crossing Symmetry is a feature of Quantum Field Theory that says
given this diagram given some new particle
they could in principle interact with -- an old particle that I know I have inside me --
I can rotate the diagram by 90 degrees and I get a new diagram that is a little bit different when I rotate it.
You know time goes from left to right in these diagrams
There's this, there's a little technical rule that if a line gets flipped from going left to right from to going right to left
I exchange a particle with an antiparticle. We're not at that level of detail here,
but the point is that rotated diagram gives me a new process with the same probability --
the same quantum amplitude -- as the old process has.
In other words, if the thing on the left can happen
where the new particle and the old particle scatter off each other,
then the thing on the right can happen where two existing particles --
two protons or two electrons or something like that -- can annihilate into each other and
create this new particle. You can produce the new particle. It can't hide from you.
And this idea that we smash particles together and look to see what comes out and hope that new particles comes out
that is what particle physicists do! We've been smashing particles together for decades
Electrons and other electrons, electrons and positrons, protons and protons, protons and antiprotons,
neutrons... We've smashed everything together that we have in the Core Theory of particle physics. We've seen what comes out
That's how we discovered the Higgs boson at the Large Hadron Collider in 2012
Is it possible that there are particles that exist that haven't yet been produced in this way?
Sure. But we know what that would mean.
Either they interact with ordinary matter so weakly that you can't make them
when you smash literally billions of particles together and none of these new particles are created.
That's possible.
But if that's possible then they're not gonna play an important role in you. They're -- you can't make them
They're just irrelevant to the processes that describe the atoms and the molecules inside you.
The other possibility is that you do make them, but then they quickly decay away.
That's what happens with the Higgs boson for example.
The Higgs boson you make it then it decays away in one zeptosecond.
A zeptosecond is ... a very short period of time. Ten to the minus 21 seconds.
So we say we've discovered the Higgs boson at CERN. We've never seen a Higgs boson
We've seen the thing the Higgs bosons decay into and if that's the way that these particles have avoided being seen
then again, they're not relevant to you and me. If you did have any in your brain, they would decay away. In a zeptosecond. Or less.
This is why we can make this kind of statement about our knowledge of the laws of physics underlying everyday life.
It's certainly -- you're welcome to imagine other new particles and forces.
But if they were there, and they were strongly interacting enough with you and me to be relevant to our everyday lives
we would have seen them already and we do not. So we know what you and I are made of.
What is remaining to do is to match this underlying Core Theory equation to the everyday life that we see
And that's where this principle called Emergence comes in.
That we have different vocabularies, different stories we can tell about the world at different levels of detail.
The story of the Core Theory with the particles the electrons and the Quantum Fields bumping into each other.
That's the microscopic version of reality. Our best current microscopic description. We may in the future do get even deeper layers,
but the layer that we have right now won't go away.
And that microscopic description is a story of Particles, Fields, Differential Equations.
The macroscopic world that we are familiar with in our everyday lives that Aristotle knew about
speaks a completely different language. There is dissipation, there's Cause and Effect.
There's a natural state for things to move in, there are reasons why
things happen rather than not happen and much of this is due to this first
item on the list here, the arrow of time. The difference between past and future.
The arrow of time is something that is absolutely central to how we think about the world.
It is so central that you don't notice it is a thing.
Aristotle -- who wrote books on absolutely everything from metaphysics to drama --
never talked about the arrow of time.
Of course the past is different from the future. That's just an obvious thing.
What is it -- what are you even asking that question about?
But there's no arrow of time in the Core Theory equation.
There was no arrow of time in Newton's equations for describing the world.
The best since the time of Isaac Newton the best ways we have of describing the world at the most fundamental
microscopic level do not distinguish between past and future in any way.
Despite that the world in which we live obviously does distinguish between the past and future in many ways.
We remember what happened yesterday. We don't remember the future
I hope nobody here remembers the future. You can make choices right? So like right now you could decide
that you think this is the most boring lecture you've ever heard you can leave you don't need to be here for the next half
of the lecture. But you cannot right now decide not to have come to the lecture.
You cannot make a decision that affects the past, right?
There's an asymmetry of influence. Where does that come from
if the underlying laws treat the past and future symmetrically?
Well, it all comes down to this egg breaking.
If you understand the egg breaking, you understand why all these things are true.
This egg breaking illustrates the increase of Entropy or disorderliness -- the Second Law of Thermodynamics,
(which is going to be a theme of the Royal Institution's Advent Calendar)
Entropy increases. You clean your room, you leave it to its own devices, your room gets messier over time
that's a fundamental law of physics. Of course you can clean it again.
But that's because your room is not a closed system.
In an isolated system or in the universe as a whole
entropy increases the universe becomes more disorderly.
The reason why is because there are more ways to be
low-- more ways to be high entropy than to be low entropy.
You give me an orderly arrangement like an unbroken egg, it is easy to break it.
There's a lot more ways to arrange the molecules in the egg in the form of a broken egg or scrambled eggs
than there are in a very delicately chosen arrangement of the unbroken egg.
That's half of the reason why there is an arrow of time. There's more ways to be high entropy to be low entropy.
But the other half is the universe was low entropy in the past.
That's more of a puzzle. Why was the universe lower entropy, more orderly, yesterday than it is today?
I can tell you the answer. It's because it was even lower Entropy the day before yesterday.
And the reason why that's true is because it was even lower entropy the day before that
and this logic goes back 13.8 billion years to the Big Bang.
There's no fundamental arrow of time, just like there's no fundamental arrow of space in the laws of physics.
If you were an astronaut doing experiments, there'd be no difference between up down left right forward backward in front of you.
You could rotate yourself out there in space it wouldn't make any difference.
Here in this room, there's an arrow of space.
If I let go the book it falls. I could predict what direction it's gonna fall in -- it goes down.
We don't think that's built into the nature of reality,
we think it's because we live in the vicinity of an influential object, namely the Earth.
What I'm telling you is that the arrow of time is exactly the same way.
It's tempting, it's natural to think that the difference between past and future is somehow inherent in the nature of reality
but it's not. It's because we live in the aftermath of an influential event -- the Big Bang
That had a very low entropy, was a very organised system. We don't know why. If you want to know why -- well no one knows why
If you want to think about why I wrote a book that was the first book I wrote, _From Eternity to Here_
You can buy that, that's where this figure is from.
So what this is revealing to us, is that unlike an Aristotelian view which was teleological --
things were directed toward a future goal. They were headed toward going back to their natural state of being.
If anything, the macroscopic world is Echinological
which is from the Greek words start or beginning. The special state of the universe was where it began.
We don't know why it began in such a special state, but since then it's just been winding down.
That's all it's been doing. There is no future goal or place toward which we're going.
That increase of entropy is sufficient to explain all the differences between past and future.
We can't go through all of them -- that would require another book, or another lecture --
but let's think about the idea of a memory or a record
Some artifact some feature of the present day that gives us knowledge of the past in a reliable way.
So maybe that's literally a memory in your head, maybe it's a photograph maybe you're walking down the street on the sidewalk you see a broken egg
I claim that the evidence that you have (there's an egg broken on the sidewalk) gives you different leverage over the past than over the future.
You can ask yourself: what does the future of the egg hold?
Well many things are possible right? It could just sit there, someone could clean it up, a dog could come by and eat it,
it could be washed away.  There's many different possible futures.
What was the past of the egg probably like? Well, with very large probability
there was an unbroken egg and somebody dropped it, right?
We can say something much more specific and informative about the past given this evidence of the egg right now
than we can about the future. Why is that?
Again, if all you knew were the deepest laws of physics that equation I showed you or Newton's laws or whatever
your ability to extrapolate toward the past and future would be identical.
You have some knowledge of the worlds present state, but it is incomplete
You have this macroscopic configuration of the egg but you don't know what all the atoms and molecules are doing.
The number of things the egg could possibly do toward the future is exactly equal to the number of things that could have been doing in the past
if all you know is the fundamental laws of physics. But you know something else.
You know that the early universe had a low entropy. You know that our past --
something that philosophers have sadly labelled the Past Hypothesis -- (which is most boring label I've ever heard)
but the Past Hypothesis says the universe started with low entropy
and that provides an anchor that provides an asymmetry between what we know about the past and what we know about the future.
So you have not only the present information, but also
that past anchor and that lets you infer features of what actually happened in the past
If you have an egg broken on the sidewalk there used to be an unbroken egg
If you have a photograph of you ten years old wearing a red sweater, you probably were wearing a red sweater that day.
We all know that -- we've all heard, right, that there's this general tendency of the universe to wind down and
evolve toward its heat death over time. And there is in my country, there's a controversy over
what is called Creationism. Some people think that if you think that there's a fundamental feature of the world
where things just go to more more disorderly states that is incompatible with the
appearance over a cosmological history of things like you and me.
Because we're not low entropy. How is it possible that such highly organized things like you and me could just pop into existence
in a world that is generally becoming more and more disorganized?
And scientists have an immediate glib answer to this: the Earth and its biosphere is not a closed system
It's not isolated. You can clean your room. There are things called refrigerators.
If you put your bottle of champagne in the refrigerator its entropy will go down as it cools, okay?
So therefore there's no contradiction with the second law of thermodynamics that low entropy things
like you and me came to be as the universe expanded and cooled.
On the other hand, just because you can clean your room doesn't mean you will clean your room.
Some of you may have experienced this with children or even yourselves
So the fact that the Earth is not a closed system allows for the appearance of organized systems like you and me
but it doesn't explain why it happened. The explanation is of course incomplete. We don't know the full answer.
But it relies on the fact that there's a difference between simplicity and complexity.
There's an axis if you like between simple systems and complex systems;
another axis between low entropy organized things and high entropy disorganized things.
Being disorganized does not mean being simple or being complex.
Think about one of my favorite examples: mixing cream into coffee. On the left, you have a low entropy situation
all the cream's on the top, all the coffee's on the bottom.
As time goes on, the cream mixes into the coffee. On the right, you have a high entropy situation everything is mixed together
That's a natural flow of time from past to future.
But think about the system on the left. It is very simple.
Here the technical definition of simplicity vs. complexity is:
"How long do you have to talk to me to describe the system in full detail?" How many bytes of information do you need?
On the left, all the cream's on the top all the coffee's on the bottom. It's very simple.
On the right, everything is mixed together. It's also very simple.
It's in between, it's where those tendrils of cream and coffee are mixing together in some intricate fractal pattern
that's when things look complex. So there's a natural tendency as the universe ages for entropy to increase
but at the same time complexity first increases and then decreases.
It's not only that complex systems are allowed to come into existence when entropy is increasing.
In a very real sense, they do come into existence because entropy is increasing
or at least they can maintain themselves, they can maintain structure and order and self-repair
because we're in a very low entropy universe that is only gradually becoming more and more disorderly.
And it's not just cups of coffee and cream that this is true for this is true for the universe.
So here is the history of our observable universe in a very brief presentation
It started out -- we don't know what happened at the Big Bang, but one second after the Big Bang we know
what the universe was like. It was hot, dense, and smooth. That's it.
That's a very simple explanation a very simple description. I didn't take that many bytes to give it to you.
As the universe expands and cools, it becomes increasingly lumpier because gravity pulls things together
So a few hundred thousand years after the Big Bang we get the cosmic background radiation
A snapshot of what the universe looked like when it first became transparent
Tiny variations in density from place to place, but still pretty smooth
Now fourteen billion years after the Big Bang the universe is very complicated.
We've formed galaxies and stars and planets and Biospheres and lecture halls. It's a very complicated part of the universe
But we can keep going. We discovered in 1998 that the universe is not only expanding, but accelerating
It's expanding faster and faster, which means it's never gonna stop
According to our best current theories what will happen is the stars will burn out
10 to the 15 years 1 quadrillion years from now the last star will stop shining - Sorry
All those stars are gonna fall into black holes and Stephen Hawking taught us in 1970s that even
black holes don't last forever. They give off radiation. So 10 to the 100 years from now
What used to be called a Google before the search engine took over the term 10 to the 100 years from now
There'll be nothing left in the observable universe it will literally be nothing but empty space
Nothing but empty space is very simple, but it is very high entropy.
Everything's very far apart, so there's lots of different arrangements for the things that do exist in the universe
So the entropy of this universe just increases, but the complexity first increases and then decreases
This is a natural robust generic way that complexity can come into being
What we want to do -- that's the easy part -- what we want to do is take that natural robust simple story and apply it
to the real evolution of complicated structures like life here on Earth.
So for me the epiphany was one day I was taking a plane ride to a conference and I was actually interested in the origin of life
I was reading a paper, a technical paper on the relationship between physics and the origin of life
So I'm sitting there reading my paper the guy in the plane seat next to me starts talking
And you know as a theoretical physicist and cosmologist you meet a lot of people who have theories
About the universe that they would like to explain to you.
So this guy looks at my paper, and he says, "Oh yes, I'm familiar with that work. In fact
I can tell you the purpose of life." Like okay, long plane ride ahead lay it on me.
He said the purpose of life is to hydrogenate carbon dioxide
Not what I expected his theory to be. Turns out the guy sitting next to me was
Dr. Michael Russell of the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena one of the world's leading researchers on the origin of life
What are the odds? Well turns out we were going to the same conference so it's not completely a coincidence
Everything happens for a reason, remember
So Mike Russell's theory which is not universally accepted. We don't know how life began
there are different competing ideas. Mike Russell's theory -- he has one of the good ideas
His idea is that in certain environments of the early Earth
were in a low entropy configuration. In particular all the carbon atoms were in the form of carbon dioxide
which happens to be relatively low entropy
Given all the water and hydrogen around them, they could be in the form of methane, CH4
That would be a higher entropy configuration.
In some sense, to be a little bit poetic about it, it "wants" to be in the form of methane. That would be higher entropy.
But there is no simple chemical reaction that goes from carbon dioxide to methane while increasing the entropy all along there's a barrier in between
You need to first lower the entropy to get to the higher entropy state
So Mike Russell's idea is that even though there's no simple chemical reaction
There is a network of complex chemical reactions that could do the trick
and that in the right circumstances that could happen and be self-sustaining
and that self-sustaining metabolism could then break free of its original environment and become the precursor to life
So it's more than just a pretty story. He actually made a prediction.
He's a geologist by training and he said, you know if this is true there must exist under the ocean floor a certain kind of geological formation
warm alkaline hydrothermal event -- hydrothermal vents where this kind of chemistry is going on
and after he made the prediction they found them. This is what you live for in science.
This is a picture of the Lost City hydrothermal formation deep underneath the Atlantic Ocean in the Mid-Atlantic Ridge
It's been it lasts for tens of thousands of years
So Mike Russell and other people think that maybe this is the kind of place where life began
We don't know -- I'm not pushing this theory necessarily -- what I'm pointing out is that rather than saying
"But entropy increases why should something as complex as life ever come to be?"
The -- it's very very plausible that the appearance of life depended on the fact that entropy tends to increase
so you actually find the complexity depends on entropy increasing and vice versa
The reason why entropy could increase in this system is only because you had a complex network of reactions
And that of course continues to the present day.
We live in an open system. We live here on Earth.
You ask yourself, "What good is the Sun? What does the Sun do for us here on Earth?"
You might think, well we get energy from the Sun. But that's not quite right.
It's true that we get energy from the Sun. But we give the same amount of energy back to the universe
We radiate back into the universe the same amount of energy that we get from solar radiation
The difference is that for every one photon of light we get from the Sun -- visible light --
we radiate twenty photons of infrared light back to the universe
with on average one twentieth of the energy each, but twenty times the entropy
The thing that the Sun gives us is not just energy, but energy in a concentrated low entropy form
and we then photosynthesize, chew our cud, eat our cows, give lectures, write books
All of that, all those processes increase the entropy of the universe along the way
Then we give it back to the universe in the form of infrared radiation
So we are sustained by increasing entropy. Back in the 1800s, it was a reasonable hypothesis
that Life was a Thing. We thought for instance that Heat was a Thing
if you put a hot object next to a cold object they equilibrate -- they come to the same temperature -- so people said
"Well, that's kind of like putting two vessels with a fluid in it
the fluid comes to the same level
there must be a heat fluid that flows from the hot thing to the cold thing."
Not true!  Don't believe anything I just said. Heat is not a fluid; heat is a feature
It is a way of talking about the motions of the atoms and molecules
Life is the same way. Life is not a force or a substance that is in your body and then leaves
it is a feature. It is a way of talking about what is happening inside you.
The bad news is that that means it will end someday but we'll get to that in a second.
I have lots of bad news. Don't -- don't worry
The good news is that once this happens once you get life
once you get this chemical reaction that sustains itself and reproduces and wants to keep going
there's this wonderful thing that kicks in called evolution
If there's different ways the chemical reaction could arrange itself and some of them were more robust and more likely to survive
Professor Darwin would tell you that's what's going to happen
Those more robust ones are likely to dominate the future ecosystem in that particular environment
And what that means is that we can once again change our vocabularies
just as we change our vocabulary - going from particles and atoms to eggs and entropy and and time
We can change our vocabulary when we start talking about biology and evolution
because the new words that creep into our vocabulary are words of purpose and reasons why
Why is it that a giraffe has a very long neck? You could say if you want to be annoying about it,
"Well because of the laws of physics and the initial conditions of the universe, that's why giraffe has its long neck."
That's the answer to every question, "why is something true?" Laws of physics and the initial conditions of the universe.
But it's not the only possible answer. In fact, it's not a very sensible answer, right? There's another answer that says,
Well, giraffes had mutations in their genes and some of them got longer necks and those were able to reach
sources of food up on trees that other animals with which they were competing were not able to reach
and therefore over successive generations the longer and longer necks survived and flourished
and they were naturally selected to be like that. So in a very real sense the purpose of the giraffes long neck
is to help it reach food sources that it couldn't otherwise reach
Where did that purpose come in? Did it did someone put it there? No, it evolved naturally, but that doesn't mean it's fake
It doesn't mean it's an illusion. It is a useful emergent vocabulary for talking about what happens at the macroscopic level
And you're probably willing to believe that if I'm just talking about life and biology.
It's where it comes to thinking and neuroscience and consciousness that people tend to get off the bus.
And of course just like with the origin of life we don't understand the origin of consciousness or what it really is.
What we can do is suggest occasional steps in the history of life which might help us understand
why consciousness became an interesting part of biology.
This guy up here the C Elegans nematode kind of flat worm is a little model organism
that biologists like to study. In your brain the cells doing the thinking are the neurons
There's something like 85 billion neurons in your brain
and different neurons are connected to each other and a big project for modern neuroscience
is studying the connectome -- the way that all the neurons in your brain are connected to each other
We're gonna start with a simpler system. We're going to start with C elegans. We have its connectome
We've mapped it out. C elegans flatworm has exactly 302 neurons
So you can actually count them, and then now you counted them and see how they connect to each other
We're trying to figure out what they're for what they do in the flatworm. There is a paper that came out
I'm not sure if it's correct or not -- theoretical physicist remember. But there's a claim that is very interesting one
that says they can identify one of those neurons whose job it is
to tell the nematode whether it's looking at itself or the rest of the world
Is this thing in front of me is this dirt is this water, or is this just my tail right?
This this one part of one neuron its job is to sort of
Have a little bit of self-awareness, a little bit of "Well, this is me not the rest of the world"
now you can see why if that developed just through the natural fluctuations
and mutations of evolution it would be an advantageous thing to keep around. We have much more highly developed
self-awareness and you can imagine other steps along the way.
Malcolm McIver who is a mechanical engineer at Northwestern he studies fish and
how in particular fish sense their surroundings. So he points out that a fish with its eyes eyes are very ubiquitous in life
They developed multiple independent times in the course of evolution. But eyes aren't that great if you're underwater
you know you can see tens of meters at most. The attenuation length of light is just not that far and
you're swimming at meters per second. So if you're a fish every time you see something new you have seconds to react to it
maybe a second, right? So the evolutionary pressure is to make a decision really quickly is this
food is this friendly, or is this foe and I should run away?
So you don't need to think too much if you're a fish, but when you hop onto land
Now the attenuation length of photons is kilometers. You can see off to the horizon. You can see essentially forever
It's possible that you now see something coming long before you need to react
So there's a new evolutionary pressure that starts exerting itself that if you just through the randomness of evolution
develop the ability to contemplate different hypothetical scenarios
Then you have a new way of winning the struggle for survival. That is to say, up on land it pays to develop an imagination
Not just an awareness of yourself, but the ability to put yourself hypothetically into different situations and say what is the right thing to do?
We don't know if any of this is right, okay?
We don't know how consciousness evolved or even we don't even know the right definition of consciousness, but you can imagine
stories like this will be put together by the progress of biology and neuroscience over the years
The only thing that I really care about I really want to stress
is that there's nothing that we know about consciousness that is incompatible with the idea
that we are made of the particles and fields of the core theory obeying that equation
Here I have a picture of my brain. This is actually my it's not my brain it's the skull so I was in it's not to scale either but
I was in a machine MEG Magneto Encephalogram machine and there were
sensors placed on my skull that looked for magnetic fields you've seen fMRI
pictures which are able very very good at locating things spatially in the brain But their time resolution is not very good
An MEG has great time resolution because what happens is
Your brain is made of particles in the core theory in that includes your neurons so when your neurons talk to each other
electrically charged particles race down the neurons and as people who stood at this desk long before me could tell you
when charged particles start moving you create a magnetic field. So this sense is. The magnetic field that those blue, and red splotches are the magnetic
fields the south and north poles coming in and out of my skull when I think a thought
This is just a reminder of something you already know which is that thoughts are associated with real physical things
happening in your brain. They're not abstract things outside our physical bodies there used to be a theory that they were right Rene Descartes
very famously promulgated a theory of mind-body dualism. He was a skeptic and he came up with a "Cogito, ergo sum" argument, I think therefore I am,
I cannot doubt the existence of my mind because it is the thing doing the doubting But he says it's very easy for me to doubt the existence of my body
so if I can doubt the existence of my body but not the existence of my mind they must be two separate things. He wrote books about this became very famous
died a tragic death in the cold, but that's a whole another story, so... There weren't a lot of tenured faculty
positions at the time of Descartes in the 1600s so one had to be nice to potential patrons
So he got to know this young lady Princess Elizabeth of Bohemia. His his aim wasn't very good. They were in exile and didn't have a lot of money
Princess Elizabeth and her family, but fortunately Princess Elizabeth was a genius. She was a wonderful thinker very highly educated
She devoured Descartes' books and she didn't agree with what he said. And they struck up a correspondence which is a wonderful thing to read I encourage you to go look up
Princess Elizabeth's correspondence with Descartes and Elizabeth says, "look, this mind-body stuff I just don't know -- you're saying that there's a mind that is literally
Immaterial that has no location in space and yet it clearly
Influences what our bodies do when I talk presumably my mind has something to do with the words, I'm saying
So Elizabeth wants to know how does the immaterial mind causally affect the material body?
And Descartes in response drew pictures like this. This is yeah. It was back in the days
They were just begin to open people up right so they knew that your brain came in two different hemispheres
There seemed to be one organ in the brain that there's only one of them it was not broken in two
that was the pineal gland that little teardrop shaped thing right there, so Descartes says well
You only have one mind, one soul, so I bet that the soul talks to your body via the pineal gland
Yeah, no one else believed that either in the 1600s. It was not a very effective
Hypothesis for understanding what was going on. And so Elizabeth kept pushing on him, and he never really gave a very good answer
Today we would have a much sharper version of Elizabeth's question
Remember this I know you love this equation right. If Princess Elizabeth were here today she would say Renee,
Tell me how the immaterial mind pushes around the quantum fields of the core theory this
Equation tells me what's going to happen in the quantum fields of the core theory without any reference to an immaterial mind
So you must be saying this equation is wrong in some way. Tell me how and there's still no answer to that
So the conclusion that I want to draw is not that I understand what consciousness is or how it came about
But that we should be able to understand it without invoking violations of the physical laws
that make up you and me. Does that mean that we are non-autonomous robots?
Well, I don't think so. So the philosophy that I try to elucidate in the book is called poetic naturalism
The idea is that there's naturalism says there's only one world the natural world But poetic means there's many ways of talking about the world
there's many different levels of description whether it's atoms versus gas in a room or
Emergent purpose for the neck of the giraffe or even things like making choices
you can describe yourself as a set of particles and forces obeying the core theory or you can describe yourself as a person.
And people make choices. If you choose to describe yourself using only
Atoms and molecules, then there is no such thing as free will and there's no such thing as the ability to make a choice
But if as real actual people do you describe yourself as a person then you can't help
But attribute to yourself the ability to make choices
So if you want to say can free will the ability to make choices be real and true even though we are made of atoms
Yes, of course it can in the same way that any emergent property can be real the different vocabularies work within
themselves you can't start a sentence in one language, and then end it in another one and
Once you accept that then the same thing goes true for more judgmental
value-laden propositions. Is there right and wrong? Is there a way to live in the world with meaning and compassion? Well yes
It's nowhere to be found in the fundamental atoms but nowhere to be found in fundamentals of tables either or water
right these are higher level emergent properties and caring and meaning and purpose
are the same kind of thing. Now that bothers people because they want things like right and wrong to be objective right
Even the most hardcore scientifically minded person wants to say well. I will someday do so much science that I will tell you right from wrong
I will discover how to live as a human being I'm here to say that it's never going to happen more bad news
Sorry. The good news is that you can choose what to label right and wrong and no one can stop you
you construct your own morality the analogy I like to use is
think of the rules of chess. The rules of chess are not fixed by the laws of physics. We made them up
We all agree on that, but that doesn't mean they're arbitrary that doesn't mean you could make up any old rules and they'd be just as good
When we made up the rules of chess we had goals in mind.
And when we make up the rules of right and wrong and living together in the world we likewise have
Goals in mind we will not always agree there will always be people who would rather play go than play chess
We might have to sort of come to an understanding of what our overlap is, but that doesn't mean that we're adrift
It doesn't mean that just because the universe doesn't tell us how to behave there is no way to behave
All right the final piece of bad news. I already sort of foreshadowed this, but you are all going to die
So biologists like to study these scaling relations. How one biological property depends on another one so it turns out that larger animals live longer
But their hearts beat slower, and it is particular kind of animals like mammals for example, these effects cancel out, in mammals very roughly speaking
Every mammal is granted one and a half billion heartbeats for their lifetime
on this axis you can figure out you tell me how heavy an object is a Mammal is I will tell you how fast its heart beats
And how long it's gonna live. Now we human beings heart beats and you know once per second right
60 or 70 times a minute so that puts us at about 40 years and that's about right
That's how long we used to live back in the state of nature of course these days we have
Obamacare and the National Health and pasteurized milk So we have increased our lifespan
We live twice as long as we should so that gives us three billion heartbeats to our lives before we die
And if you believe in the core theory do you believe that we are made of particles obeying the laws of physics
Then there is no life after death there's no place for the information that is contained in your neurons
to go when you die because it's in your neurons and the atoms that are there they stay in your body even when you you die.
And that can be sad. You you might want to be I would have liked to live not maybe forever forever is a long time
But I think I could keep things interesting for a few hundred thousand years before they got boring
I only get three billion heartbeats and three billion is an interesting number
It's sort of a big number, but it's not that big. I mean you've squandered a couple thousand heartbeats
Just over the course of this lecture Knowing that you have about 3 billion heartbeats allocated to you
Makes every heartbeat seem precious, right? It's not just like a little thing that will grow into something
After we die because this is it every one of those heartbeats is meaningful to you Because you only have a finite number
So the good news. This is not going to sound like good news after all that bad news, but the good news is
On the one hand we are very very small ok this is the famous Hubble Ultra Deep Field
an image of galaxies if you take us telescope and point it at the sky and you click the shutter on the camera
and you just leave it open this is what you will see if your telescope is the Hubble Space Telescope. This is what you will see
Our universe is alive with galaxies our our galaxy the Milky Way has about a hundred billion stars
Before last week I was able to say there's about a hundred billion Galaxies in the observable universe, I don't know if you following the news
But they discovered that the density of galaxies is actually 20 times higher than we thought it was. There's about two trillion
galaxies in the observable universe. Every one of these dots even tiny dots. That's a galaxy with a hundred billion stars
Who knows how many royal institutions they have where there's a lecture going on there with a picture of us up there. We seem very small
That's the that's the last piece of bad news the good news is, we took this picture
Right we're exactly there. You go appreciate the good news We are very very tiny insignificant the universe is not about us if the universe was about us
If there was some purpose to the world that was for our greater glory, we would not be
Around a medium sized planet around a medium sized star in a galaxy with 100 billion stars in a universe with two trillion galaxies
We'd be more central. And if you look at the ancient pictures of the world we were always much more central than the modern view had it
despite that we are the little part of the universe in this age when things are complex and interesting
that has developed the capacity for self-awareness and reflection
and thinking and rational thought and writing books and buying books by the way
and that should make us feel pretty good. We don't always do very well at it
I think both in my country in yours there are examples in recent political history where things have gone
Not right. But we have the ability to be rational to think to invent to discover to create new things to care about each other in ways
That other parts of the universe just don't care about each other and that's that capacity that we have as fleeting as
Life is it's up to us What to make of it the fact that we are made of atoms and particles obeying the laws of physics doesn't stop us
From caring about ourselves the rest of the world our legacies the people next to us right now
So that's a choice that we can make completely compatible with the laws of physics I urge you all to choose very wisely. Thank you